Guide to the Wilfrid S. Sellars Papers, 1899-1990 ASP.1991.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Wilfrid S. Sellars Papers
1899-1990
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Sellars, Wilfrid
ASP.1991.01
82.25 Linear Feet (197 document cases, 1 oversize box, and 28 boxes of dictabelts)
Wilfrid S. Sellars was an American philosopher who made significant contributions to Philosophy of Science, Epistemology, and many other areas within philosophy. He was particularly noted for his contributions to Metaphysics and to Philosophy of Mind. The collection consists of manuscripts of nearly all of Sellars' work (including autograph manuscripts of many these texts), reading notes, preliminary notes for further development, drafts of articles, working papers, correspondence, teaching materials and lecture notes. The correspondence includes exchanges with many of the leading philosophers of the twentieth century. There are also Ph.D. theses for students supervised by Sellars, personal correspondence, and drafts and typescripts for materials written by other philosophers. Materials from the work of Roy Wood Sellars can also be found here. Digital reproductions of this collection are available online.
Biography
Wilfrid S. Sellars (1912-1989) was a major American philosopher who was active in the middle part of the 20th century. His father was the prominent Canadian-American philosopher Roy Wood Sellars. Wilfrid Sellars's family traveled in Europe during his childhood and youth and he attended educational institutions in France and in Germany. He attended the University of Michigan, receiving an A.B. degree in 1933. He then attended the University of Buffalo, located in Buffalo, New York, from which he obtained an AM in 1934. He then traveled to England, where as a Rhodes Scholar he enrolled at Oriel College, Oxford. He earned a BA from Oriel in 1936 and an MA in 1940. In 1938 Sellars took up his first academic post as Assistant Professor of Philosophy at the University of Iowa.
Sellars served in the United States Navy during World War II. After the war, in 1946, he moved to the University of Minnesota, as an assistant professor of Philosophy. At Minnesota he established a productive professional relationship with Herbert Feigl, working with him at the Minnesota Center for the Philosophy of Science. In 1950 the two of them founded Philosophical Studies, a forum for publishing articles and books in the new sub-discipline of analytic philosophy, and were co-editors of the early volumes.
In 1956 Sellars, while at the University of London as a Special Lecturer, delivered one of his most important papers. This was later published as "Empiricism and the Philosophy of Mind." In 1958 Sellars became a Professor of Philosophy at Yale University. In 1963 Sellars moved to the University of Pittsburgh where he became the University Professor of Philosophy. Sellars remained at the University of Pittsburgh for the remainder of his active professional life.
Sellars delivered lectures in distinguished lecture series such as the John Locke Lectures Series of Oxford University. This lecture series was subsequently published as Science and Metaphysics. Other important lecture series include the Matchette Foundation lectures of 1971, given at the University of Texas and later published as "The Structure of Knowledge;" the 1973 John Dewey Lectures of the University of Chicago, later published as Naturalism and Ontology, and the 1977 Paul Carus Lectures which were later published as "Foundations for a Metaphysics of Pure Process".
Sellars was renowned as a teacher and had profound influence on many students, both undergraduate and graduate, during his teaching career. His teaching style was lively and effective and he was able to communicate core ideas in philosophy in a clear and profound way. Some of the students affected by Sellars' teaching went on to become very prominent philosophers themselves. Among these are Pedro Amaral, Bruce Aune, Robert Brandom, Hector Neri Castaneda, Paul Churchland, James Conant, John McDowell, Willem De Vries, Richard Rorty, Jay Rosenberg, Johanna Seibt, Jeffrey Sicha, Tim Triplett, and Bas Van Fraassen.
Scope and Content Notes
The Wilfrid S. Sellars Papers reflect the working life of a professional philosopher of science. Focusing on his professional pursuits in researching, writing and teaching from the 1930s through 1987, these files consist of books, correspondence, contracts, course materials, financial records, manuscripts, notes, photographs, publications, and reports. Especially significant are the manuscripts, which range from notes and working drafts in Sellars's own hand to the published articles.
Although smaller than the other series, the first series provides researchers with records pertaining to the more personal aspects of Sellars's life. The second, fifth and sixth series document the various stages of researching, writing, and editing of manuscripts employed by Sellars. The third series emphasizes Sellars's academic duties as a philosophy professor from 1938 to 1987. The fourth series highlights Sellars's contributions to the philosophy community as an editor, consultant, and lecturer, which compliment his duties as an author and professor. The seventh series documents the career of Sellars's father, Roy Wood Sellars, which is included because of the close personal and professional interactions between them.
Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available electronically, specifically Series I. Personal, Subseries 2. Educational Material and Series II. Research and Writing, Subseries 1. Handwritten Notes and Subseries 2. Pre-Publication Materials.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into seven series, loosely grouped by topic. Extensive scope and content notes are provided at the following series levels:
Series I. Personal and Biographical
Series II. Research and Writing
Series III. Academic Career
Series IV. Professional Activities
Series V. Library
Series VI. Dictabelts
Series VII. Roy Wood Sellars
The collection has been arranged into seven series, loosely grouped by topic. Extensive scope and content notes are provided at the following series levels:
Access Restrictions
The letters of recommendation are restricted. In addition all student records in Series III Subseries I -boxes 112 and 113 are restricted.
Acquisition Information
The scholarly books, journals, and offprints were donated by his heir, Susanna K. Downie to the University of Pittsburgh, Archives of Scientific Philosophy. The manuscripts, letters, dictabelts, and working drafts were sold to the University of Pittsburgh by his widow and heir, Susanna K. Downie.
Existence and Location of Copies
A portion of the Wilfrid S. Sellars Papers is dictabelts, and an inventory of this material is located in the scope and content notes for Series VI. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection contains dictabelt records which require the use of the Series 850 Dictaphone device.
Custodial History
The material within the Wilfrid S. Sellars Collection that originally derives from the work of his father, Roy Wood Sellars, and the material created by his mother, Helen Sellars, were present in the collection at the time of its sale to the University of Pittsburgh Library System's Archives of Scientific Philosophy.
Previous Citation
Wilfrid S. Sellars Papers, 1899-1990, ASP.1991.01, Archives of Scientific Philosophy, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Separated Material
The annotated books and journals, as well as the annotated offprints will be retained in the collection and housed with the manuscripts, correspondence, working drafts, and other materials from the collection. The dictabelts are stored separately in the climate controlled audio/visual room at the University of Pittsburgh's Archives Service Center.
Realism; Ethics; Ontology; Naturalism; Analysis (Philosophy); Empiricism; Epistemology; Metaphysics; Science -- Philosophy; Philosophy of mind; Sellars, Roy Wood; Sellars, Wilfrid
- Personal, 1899-1988; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  These files mostly relate to Sellars' life prior to joining the Philosophy Department at the University of Minnesota in 1946, and highlight Sellars' interests and activities beyond philosophy and academic life. The files contain correspondence, financial records, military service files, and manuscripts, as well as records pertaining to his mother and to his first wife. The files are further described in the following subseries: Correspondence and General Files, Educational Materials, and Photographs.
  - Correspondence and General Files, 1899-1988; 1.
    Scope and Contents note
    While the majority of these files center on Sellars' personal pursuits, the bibliographies, biographical material, and curriculum vitae provide succinct summaries of Sellars' professional career. The core of the personal files is the correspondence, which emphasizes the friendships that Sellars developed during his years in Europe. A large portion of the correspondence occurs between Sellars and his first wife and details the early development of their relationship. Researchers interested in understanding Sellars' personal associations with other philosophers should refer to the professional correspondence in Subseries IV. In addition to correspondence, there are financial records that are arranged topically and pertain to matters such as his salary, real estate purchases, and royalty earnings. The military service files detail his enrollment, training, and service in the United States Navy during World War II. This section also contains the personal papers of Sellars' mother and first wife. These personal papers contain legal documents relating to their estates and entrance to the United States, as well as their interest in writing.
    - Awards and certificates, 1959-1987 (Oversize 198)
    - Bibliographies, 1951-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biographies and profiles, 1964-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Colloquium on Sellarsian Philosophy, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Correspondence
      - Andler, Pierre, 1935-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Downie, Susanna, 1967-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Extended family, 1952-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Holiday greetings, 1954-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1931-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
      - Oxonian, 1964-1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Sellars, Gertrude Mary, 1937-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
      - Sellars, Helen, 1937-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Sleeth, Charles, 1936-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Curriculum vitae, 1969-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Day planners and address books, 1959-1977 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - Family records, 1931-1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Financial records
      - Correspondence on salary, 1938-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      - Medical bills, 1950-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Real estate in Connecticut, 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Real estate in Minnesota, 1948-1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Real estate in Pittsburgh, 1964-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
      - Real estate rentals, 1967-1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Royalty statements, 1964-1987 (Box 3, Folder 10-14)
    - Forms of identification, 1912-1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Genealogical research, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Memoir of 1932 Mexico trip, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Military service
      - Enrollment materials, 1942-1943 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - General, 1944-1951 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Orders and directives, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Training booklets, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous files, 1951-1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Newsletters from University High School, 1971-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1934-1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Papers of Gertrude Mary Sellars
      - Caricature, undated (Oversize 198)
      - Marriage license, will and estate, 1938-1971 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous, 1935-1960s (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Naturalization papers and passports, 1934-1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Short story materials, 1947-1959 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Papers of Helen Sellars
      - Legal, 1899-1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Translation of "Philosophy of Art," undated (Box 5, Folder 3-8)
  - Educational Material, 1922-1953; 2.
    This subseries documents Sellars' education, principally in philosophy, from his high school years in France and Germany through his graduate education at Oxford and Harvard. The bulk of the material dates from the later 1930s and emphasizes his post secondary education. The files are separated into the following sections: Early Education, Class Papers, Lecture Notes, and Miscellaneous Materials.
    The majority of documents found within this subseries have been digitized. Each digital image is represented as a PDF. The entire folder contents are scanned and represented online.
    - Early education
      The files pertaining to Sellars' early education date from 1922-1930 and focus predominately on his time at the Lycee Louis Le Grand in France. These files contain grade sheets, a graded paper and administrative files. One noteworthy document is the "philosophie" notebook, since it may be the earliest existing example of Sellars' philosophical writing. This section also contains administrative materials from a German institution attended briefly by Sellars.
      - Lycee Louis Le Grand general files, 1922-1930 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Lycee Louis Le Grand notebook on "Philosophie", undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - University of Munich material, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Papers written for courses
      This section consists of essays written by Sellars during his undergraduate and graduate education. The essays mostly date from Sellars' time at Oxford and Harvard and are arranged alphabetically by title. The essays are usually handwritten, but in about ten cases there are typed versions available. The topics covered by the essays include the works of Hume and Bradley, ancient Greek philosophy, ethics, psychology, political institutions, and English Law. Of particular interest are the essays on Kant, which cover several related topics and are supplemented by two notebooks. These notebooks contain Sellars' handwritten notes on writings by and about Kant, which generally consist of direct quotes from the original sources.
      - "Antimony of Pure Reason", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Bradley, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Comments on philosophy, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Cook Wilson, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Economics of interest, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - English law, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - "Epiphenomenalism and Emergent Materialism", undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - "An Examination of the Cogito", c. 1935 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - "The First Analogy", undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - "The First Antinomy", undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Greek skepticism, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Heraclites and Parmenides, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Hume and relations, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Induction, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - "Introduction to the Philosophy of Schelling", undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - "Is the A Priori Analytic?", undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Kant and the antimonies, 1935-1937 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - "Kant", undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - "Kant on Space", undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - "Kant Papers for H. H. Price Collection", undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Kant papers on various topics, undated (Box 6, Folder 24-25)
      - "Kant's Refutation of Idealism", undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Notes on Kant and substance, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Notes on Kant, time, direct awareness, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - "Let us first ask the question what is it that is true?", undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Nature, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - "Negation", undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - "A Note on Emergence and Predictability", undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - "Objectivity and Subjectivity in Value Theory", undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - "Outlines of a Naturalistic Cosmology", undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - "Perception", 1931-1932 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - "Political Institutions", 1935 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Prichard and Cook Wilson, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - "The Problem of Rent", undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Psychology and ethics, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Santayana and Kant, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - "The Second Analogy is....", undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - "Some Comments on Carnap's 'Scheinproblem", undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - "Some Comments on the Theory of Political Rights", undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - "Some Remarks on the Receptacle", undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - "The Sophists", 1933 (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - "Universals", undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
      - "Utility, Value & Welfare", undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Course lecture notes
      The lecture notes are handwritten notes taken by Sellars during his post-secondary education. They are filed alphabetically by lecturer and consist of both loose sheets and bound notebooks. The lecture notes are usually labeled with the lecturer's name and the topic of the course but in a few instances the lecturer is unknown. The notebooks may have one series of notes starting from the front of the notebook, and a second series starting from the back of the notebook, with the rear-forward handwriting inverted. Both types of notes may include reading lists for the course. In a few cases, there are typed, word-for-word transcriptions of the handwritten notes. Topics include the works of Hume, Lewis, Plato, Spinoza, and Wittgenstein, as well as logic, epistemology, and ethics. In addition to the lecture notes taken by Sellars, this section also contains two typed versions of notes created by Wittgenstein's students in the 1930s.
      - "Austin - Leibnitz", undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - "(Buffalo Notebook?)", 1933 (Box 7, Folder 24)
      - Carritt - Dialectical Materialism, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
      - "Demos-Plato/Huntington Math", undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
      - "Deductive Science of Ethics", undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
      - "Huntington - Postulate Theory", undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
      - 'Kneale Political Philosophy", undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Lewis - Hume and Parmenides, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Lewis - Epistemology, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Lewis - Logic, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - "Lewis - Theory Knowledge", undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - "Mure-Hegel", undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - "H.H. Price - Problems in the Theory of Knowledge", Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - "Pritchard Lectures on Berkeley's Theory of Knowledge" Trinity Term '35, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - "Pritchard - Ethics", undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - "Pritchard - The Nature of Moral Obligation", undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - "Quine - Logical Positivism", Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Ross - Unlabeled, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Ross - Kant's moral theory and ethics, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Ross - Mr. Ryle - Induction and probability, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Ross - Smith - Kant, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Ross - Stevenson - Hume, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Unknown - Economics tutorial, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Unknown - International relations, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Unknown - Isaiah Berlin reading notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Unknown - Logical positivism, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Unknown - Political history, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Unknown - Spinoza, Wittgenstein, Plato, Logic, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Wittgenstein, Ludwig. The Blue Book [typescript], c. 1937 (Box 9, Folder 12)
        Scope and Contents
        It unclear how Sellars acquired this early typescript copy of Wittgenstein's The Blue Book. Sellars dated it "Harvard 1937". The Blue Book was originally dictated to some of his students in 1933-34, to be distributed to students at Cambridge (UK) as a kind of textbook. It was jealously guarded, but one of the students to whom it was dictated was an American, Alice Ambrose, who returned to the US to teach at Smith College in 1936. It is possible she made copies and distributed them.
        The document is a typescript on standard paper with pencil annotations.
      - Wittgenstein, Ludwig. The Brown Book [typescript], c. 1937 (Box 9, Folder 13)
        The Brown Book was dictated by Wittgenstein to two people in 1934-35: Alice Ambrose and Francis Skinner. Ambrose made copies of this when she returned to the US, though this was not intended by Wittgenstein to be distributed to students; it was rather intended as a first draft of a book which eventually became his Philosophical Investigations.
        The document is a carbon copy on thinner paper used for that purpose with blue ink manuscript illustrations and diagrams.
    - Miscellaneous
      This section contains correspondence written to Sellars in regards to his education at Oxford. Primarily, this correspondence is comprised of brief notes of congratulations sent to Sellars for passing exams. There are also several letters of recommendation Sellars received from members of the Oriel College faculty. Researchers may also be interested in Sellars's correspondence with his first wife Gertrude Mary Sharp, which is located in the personal correspondence section and discusses his education and their developing relationship. In addition to correspondence, this section also contains examination booklets and exams. The majority of these files contain exam questions. However, two of the Oxford files contain Sellars's handwritten answers to examinations. Sellars's GRE scores are also located here. The remaining files document some of Sellars non-professional activities and interests while in graduate school. More specifically, it includes receipts from the doctor and bookstore, artifacts from the Jowett Society, the Oriel College Boat Club, and administrative documents dating from Sellars's time at Oxford and Harvard.
      - Address book and checkbook, 1934-1937 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Bookstore receipts, doctor's bills, 1936-1938 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1935-1956 (Box 10, Folder 3-5)
      - Exams - GRE scores, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Exams - Oxford PPE bibliography, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Exams - Oxford PPE questions, 1931-1936 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Exams - Oxford answers on general PPE, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Exams - Oxford answers on logic, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Exams - Harvard Ph.D. questions, 1925-1938 (Box 10, Folder 11)
      - Exams - University of Buffalo questions, 1934-1939 (Box 10, Folder 12)
      - Jowett Society, 1936-1937 (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Miscellaneous memorabilia, 1933-1940 (Box 10, Folder 14-15)
      - Oxford administrative and financial documents, 1934-1940 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Photographs, 1932-1987; 3.
    The vast majority of the photographs are posed portraits that document the personal and professional aspects of Wilfrid Sellars's life. The images of Wilfrid Sellars are arranged chronologically from his infancy through 1987. Additional files contain the images of other philosophers such as Gilbert Ryle, Antony Flew, and Spinoza. The family photographs feature Sellars's immediate family, such as his first wife, parents, and siblings, as well as his extended family. The miscellaneous images include photographs and negatives of unidentified individuals. In addition there are some items documenting Sellars's late interest in koi fish and lily pads.